<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sober letter, touching predestination and obduration Sent to a minister in the city of Bristol.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1679</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 30 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60717</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S4411</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R219110</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99830635</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99830635</idno>
            <idno type="VID">35088</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A60717)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 35088)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2078:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sober letter, touching predestination and obduration Sent to a minister in the city of Bristol.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Jonathan Robinson, at the Golden Lyon, in St. Paul's Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1679.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Predestination --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:35088:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SOBER LETTER, Touching Predeſtination AND OBDURATION. Sent to a MINISTER IN The City OF BRISTOL.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed for <hi>Jonathan Robinſon,</hi> at the <hi>Golden Lyon,</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard. 1679.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:35088:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:35088:2"/>
            <head>A SOBER LETTER, TOUCHING PREDESTINATION AND OBDURATION.</head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 1.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>ALthough the Doctrine of God's Eternal <hi>Predeſtinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> be an offence to many, ſome abuſe it to carnal li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, and others to deſpair; yet it is a neceſſary and uſeful Doctrine, which upon all occaſions ought to be uttered with much <hi>reverence</hi> and circumſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, to the praiſe and glory of God (as the ſame is held forth in the ſacred Scriptures) without ſome <hi>taſte</hi> of this <hi>Divine</hi> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of <hi>Predeſtination,</hi> there can be no true Faith; but either a doubtful and wavering Opinion leading to Deſpair, or elſe a vain preſumption of feigned Holineſs, whilſt men reſt upon their own Works and Performances, and not upon the Free Grace of God. There is no Doctrine that doth more beat down the pride
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:35088:3"/>of the Fleſh, that doth more exalt the Riches of God's Grace, or more eſtabliſh and ſupport the Saints in the Aſſurance of the Love of God, than this Doctrine of God's Eternal <hi>Predeſtinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> if rightly apprehended and improved. The Scripture doth uſually alledge the Eternal Purpoſe and Decree of God for ſtrengthening and confirming our Faith and Hope of Salvation; and doth not reſt in ſecond Cauſes, or in the Fruits of our Faith and Vocation; but aſcendeth up to Chriſt himſelf: In whom (as in the Head) we are elected and predeſtinated to Grace and Glory: Yea, it raiſeth us up to that everlaſting Purpoſe and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree which was in God himſelf before the Foundation of the World, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.4, 5. <hi>Matth.</hi> 11.25, 26. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.29, 30. <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.11, 16, 18, 23.2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.9.2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.19.1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.20.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>Sect. 2.</head>
               <p>As in other Points of <hi>Divinity,</hi> ſo more eſpecially in this great Myſtery of <hi>Predeſtination,</hi> we ſhould avoid vain and curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Queſtions and Speculations; uſing ſuch words and expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons concerning the ſame, as are moſt agreeable to the <hi>Holy</hi> Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures (for who ſo fit to reveal the mind of God in this great <hi>Myſtery</hi> as God himſelf?) and not according to our corrupt fancy and imagination In this caſe 'tis beſt and ſafeſt for us to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend from the loweſt degrees to the higheſt, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> doth in his Epiſtle to the <hi>Romans:</hi> ſpeaking firſt of the Law of God, and the Corruption of Man's Nature; and ſo proceeding on to the Remiſſion of Sins, and Juſtification by Chriſt; and from thence, to the ſublime Myſtery of God's Eternal <hi>Predeſtination.</hi> Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we go up from the loweſt ſtep to the higheſt, or deſcend from the higheſt to the loweſt, we muſt take heed that we run not from one Extreme to another; omitting and paſſing by the middle Cauſes or Means of Salvation and Damnation; which ought to be duly conſidered and placed between God's Eternal <hi>Decree,</hi> and the final Execution thereof. Nor ſhould the Decree of <hi>Praeterition</hi> or Reprobation be applied to any Sinner in (parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular) ſo long as he lives, without ſpecial extraordinary Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, ſeeing God (whoſe Grace and Mercy is infinite and boundleſs) may call and convert him, even at the eleventh hour,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:35088:3"/>though his ſins be never ſo great and hainous. 'Tis obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vable, that all thoſe <hi>Acts</hi> in God, which, in the matter of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation,</hi> go befor ſin, are deſcribed, rather after a <hi>negative,</hi> than poſitive manner in the Scripture; as the <hi>Not writing their names in the book of life.</hi> Rev. 13.8. <hi>They are not found written in the book of life.</hi> Rev. 20.15. <hi>Ye are not of my Sheep.</hi> Joh. 10.26. <hi>I never knew you.</hi> Matth. 7.23. <hi>The Election hath obtained it, the reſt</hi> (i e. thoſe who are not elected) <hi>were blinded.</hi> Rom. 11.7.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 3.</head>
               <p>God's Decree of <hi>Reprobation</hi> is not the cauſe of ſin, but Man himſelf is the cauſe of ſin; <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7.29. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.31, 32. <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.14. Reprobation being part of <hi>the Decree,</hi> and the Decree nothing elſe but God himſelf decreeing, cannot be the cauſe of ſin: which is ſo contrary to God (who is <hi>Holineſs</hi> it ſelf.) His Decree may be ſaid to be the <hi>Antecedent</hi> of Sin, and Sin to be the <hi>Conſequent</hi> of the Decree, not the Effect of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree. Upon this occaſion, we ſhould always remember that approved <hi>diſtinction</hi> between a proper Cauſe, and an Antece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent: Life is the <hi>Antecedent</hi> of death, and ſight of blindneſs. And, as it is impoſſible that there ſhould be <hi>Death</hi> where there hath not been Life, or Blindneſs where there hath not been <hi>Sight</hi> foregoing; ſo it is as impoſſible, that either Life ſhould be the cauſe of Death, or Sight the cauſe of Blindneſs fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing. God willeth not Sin <hi>as</hi> Sin; therefore <hi>Reprobation</hi> is not the cauſe of Sin: God willeth the <hi>Permiſſion</hi> of Sin; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Reprobation is the <hi>Antecedent</hi> thereof. For the better guiding and regulating our Judgments in this great point, we muſt conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>three</hi> diſtinctions. 1. Between God's Willing Sin <hi>as</hi> Sin, and his Willing the being; or <hi>permiſſion,</hi> or the ordering of Sin for the Glory of Divine Juſtice and Mercy. 2. Between a Cauſe and an <hi>Antecedent.</hi> 3. Between a <hi>Conſequent</hi> and an Effect.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 4.</head>
               <p>Sin is the cauſe of Puniſhment and Damnation; God puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:35088:4"/>no man, condemneth no man, but for Sin; <hi>Original,</hi> or A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual, or both; <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.17. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.12. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18.20, 25, 28. Though <hi>Sin</hi> be not the Cauſe of the Decree of God (for that which is temporal cannot be the cauſe of that which is <hi>eternal</hi>) yet it is the only proper cauſe of Puniſhment and Damnation. We muſt diſtinguiſh between God's Decree of <hi>Non</hi>-Election, or Reprobation, and his deſtinating men to puniſhment, or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration to puniſhment; which is uſually called <hi>Praedamnation.</hi> As for the former, it dependeth ſolely upon the ſovereign Will and Pleaſure of God: but the latter is an <hi>Act</hi> of God's Juſtice. The one floweth from God, as he is a God of abſolute Power and <hi>Sovereignty;</hi> the other floweth from God, as he is a God of <hi>Juſtice.</hi> The Decree of Election and Reprobation is an <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manent</hi> Act in God alone, as in the Subject; and from God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, as from the Original Cauſe. But Damnation is neither originally from God, nor ſubjectively in God; but is a <hi>tranſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent</hi> Act of his Juſtice. God being infinitely wiſe, propoundeth to himſelf the Manifeſtation of his own <hi>Glory,</hi> as a moſt certain and infallible <hi>End;</hi> appointing and making all things to be <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervient</hi> thereunto: <hi>The Lord hath made all things for himſelf; yea, even the wicked for the day of evil.</hi> Prov. 16.4. And thus the Decree of God is deſcribed by the learned Biſhop <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Proteſtant <hi>Divines,</hi> to be that <hi>Act</hi> whereby God, from <hi>all E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity</hi> (according to his Free Will) did, by his <hi>unchangeable</hi> Counſel and Purpoſe, fore-appoint, and certainly determine of all things; together with their <hi>Cauſes,</hi> Effects, Circumſtances, and manner of Being, for the <hi>Manifeſtation</hi> of his awn <hi>Glory,</hi> Nor ſhould we go about to ſubject this <hi>Divine</hi> Decree to our <hi>ſhallow</hi> Capacity, or meaſure it by our depraved Reaſon; conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering that <hi>the Will</hi> of God (from whence the Decree cometh) is unſearchable. 'Tis true that all things come to paſs <hi>neceſſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> according to God's Eternal Decree; they ſhall not come to paſs in any other place or time than he hath ordained. But yet this Decree of God doth not infer a neceſſity of <hi>Conſtraint,</hi> but only of <hi>Immutability:</hi> nor doth the <hi>Decree</hi> take away, either <hi>Liberty</hi> from the reaſonable Creatures, or <hi>Contingency</hi> from ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Cauſes; but only brings them into a certain order, that is, directeth them to the determined <hi>End:</hi> whereupon the Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:35088:4"/>and <hi>Events</hi> of things are contingent or neceſſary, as the nature of the ſecond Cauſe is: Thus Chriſt (according to the <hi>Divine</hi> Decree) died neceſſarily; <hi>Act.</hi> 4.28. <hi>Act.</hi> 17.3. But yet willingly. If we reſpect the <hi>Temperature</hi> of Chriſt's Body, He might have lived longer: and therefore, in this reſpect, May be ſaid to have died <hi>contingently.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 5.</head>
               <p>The Doctrine of God's-Eternal <hi>Predeſtination</hi> (rightly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood) is ſo far from being a prejudice or hindrance to the Uſe of Means tending to Holineſs and Sanctification, as that the uſe of the Means is the proper Effect and Fruit of the Decree of God: the right Knowledge and Conſideration whereof is a moſt effectual Motive to a conſtant and conſcionable uſe of the Means. And therefore, that is a moſt wicked Speech (which implyeth a mere Contradiction) If I be elected, howſoever I live, I ſhall be ſaved: And if I be not elected, live I never ſo well, I ſhall be damned. Satan, by this wicked Suggeſtion, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vides the End and the Means aſunder, which God hath joyned together. The Decree of God conſiſts not only of the End with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Means, nor of the Means without the End; but of both together. <hi>God having choſen us to ſalvation, through ſanctification: of the ſprit, and belief of the Truth.</hi> 2 Theſ. 1.13.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 6.</head>
               <p>The <hi>Command</hi> and Invitation of God in the preaching of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> is the <hi>Rule</hi> of our Faith and Obedience; and not the <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret</hi> Decree of God. Nor muſt we confound the Decree of <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtination</hi> with the Precepts of Faith and Obedience: God's re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed <hi>Preceptive</hi> Will ſhews what the Lord approves (as good in it ſelf) and what ought to be performed by us: Not that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one that hears the Goſpel preached, ſhall have <hi>Effectual</hi> Grace to perform it; but yet it is the duty of every one to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, and believe on Jeſus Chriſt, and obey the Voice of God in the <hi>Diſpenſation</hi> of his Goſpel. The Doctrine of <hi>Predeſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> (as ſet forth in the Scriptures) is commanded to be taught
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:35088:5"/>and learned; and being ſoberly and wiſely handled, is very uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, both to the Godly and the Wicked. But the <hi>perſonal</hi> Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication thereof before Faith, in point of <hi>Election;</hi> or, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring this Life, in point of <hi>Reprobation;</hi> is unwarrantable, and many ways hurtful. And truly, it is a great Sin againſt the Grace and Mercy of God in the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> for any man or woman to conclude that he or ſhe is a <hi>Reprobate,</hi> becauſe final Unbelief and Diſobedience (the Conſequent of Reprobation) cannot be known before Death. No man knoweth who are <hi>reprobate</hi> but God, and thoſe to whom God revealeth it in his Word. But the <hi>Reprobation</hi> of any particular perſon (now living) is not to be found in the Scriptures, nor is it revealed in an ordinary way to us.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 7.</head>
               <p>All the Elect of God, <hi>firſt</hi> or laſt, ſhall truly believe on Chriſt, and be converted to him (Saving Faith being the Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect or Fruit of Election.) <hi>All that the Father hath given to Chriſt, ſhall come to him.</hi> Joh. 6.37. Joh. 10.36. <hi>Whom he did predeſtinate, them he alſo called.</hi> Rom. 8.30. <hi>The Election hath obtained it.</hi> Rom. 11.7. <hi>And as many as were ordained to eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal life believed.</hi> Act. 13.48. <hi>It is called the faith of God's Elect.</hi> Tit. 1.1. <hi>It is according to Election.</hi> Rom. 11.5. In which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, 'tis as certain, that all the Elect of God (though many of them are yet Unbelievers) ſhall believe and be ſaved, as it is certain that they are ſaved who are already in <hi>Heaven.</hi> As for others, God (who may do with his own what he pleaſeth) juſtly witholds from them <hi>Grace</hi> to cure their Unbelief and <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitency: To them it is not given.</hi> Matth. 13.11. Moral Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitency, and <hi>Enmity</hi> of Man's Will againſt God, is common, both to the Elect and <hi>Reprobate</hi> (they being alike ſinful and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt by Nature:) only God is pleaſed to <hi>cure</hi> the one, and not the other, of their Natural Unbelief and Impenitency. Touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the latter ſort, God may be ſaid to be the Phyſical Cauſe (not of their Unbelief, but) why their Unbelief remains uncu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: As a <hi>Phyſician,</hi> able to cure a Diſeaſe (which yet he is not bound to cure) is the cauſe, not of the Diſeaſe it ſelf, but why
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:35088:5"/>the Diſeaſe is not cured: yet is he not the Moral and Blameable, but the Phyſical and unblameable Cauſe thereof, becauſe he is not bound to cure it. This Cure cannot be effected in the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regenerate, only by outward Means, without the <hi>Internal</hi> Effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catious Operation of the Spirit of God. The <hi>Iſraelites</hi> had <hi>ſeen</hi> with their Eyes the great <hi>Signs</hi> and Myracles which God had <hi>wrought</hi> for them: yet withal, it is ſaid, that <hi>God had not given them a heart to perceive, nor eyes to ſee, nor ears to hear, unto this day:</hi> Deut. 29.3, 4. that is, he had not <hi>cured</hi> them of their Spiritual Blindneſs and unbelief, by the inward <hi>Illumination</hi> and Operation of his Spirit: for, as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith well,<note place="margin">Quantam libet praebuerit patien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam, niſi Deus dederit quis apat penitentiam? Contr. Julian, Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lag lib. <hi>5.</hi> c p. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Though God afford never ſo great patience (in reſpect of outward Means) yet, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs God give Grace, who can truly repent of his Sins?</hi> And this Grace he gives to one, and not to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, according to his good pleaſure. The bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Apoſtle, in anſwering that <hi>great</hi> Objection, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.19. Why doth God yet find fault with the Hardneſs and Rebellion of Man's heart, ſeeing no Man can reſiſt the Divine Will, nor can he cure himſelf of this hardneſs of heart? hath recourſe for ſatisfaction (not to the ill <hi>deſert,</hi> and ſinfulneſs of Man, but) to the <hi>Sovereignty</hi> and Dominion of God over his Creatures; which ſurely is as great and abſolute, as that which the <hi>Potter</hi> hath over the <hi>Clay;</hi> who maketh <hi>Veſſels</hi> of what <hi>faſhion</hi> he will, and for what <hi>end</hi> he will. So, <hi>God hath mercy on whom he will have mercy, and whom he will he hardeneth: and who art thou, O Man, that replyeſt againſt God? Shall the thing formed ſay to him that formed it, why haſt thou made me thus?</hi> It becomes not the Creature to <hi>quarrel</hi> with God, or <hi>diſpute</hi> with him concerning this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter (though the Creature cannot comprehend the <hi>reaſonableneſs</hi> thereof.) This may well ſatisfie and ſilence us, that the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> doth not go about to <hi>juſtifie</hi> God's Courſes (here mentioned) from the Conſideration of Man's <hi>Sinfulneſs,</hi> but only from the Conſideration of God's <hi>Sovereignty,</hi> and Supreme Dominion o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver his Creatures. And, as God freely gives the <hi>Grace</hi> of Faith and Repentance to ſome Men, and not to others, to raiſe them <hi>out</hi> of Sin; ſo God gave <hi>corroborating,</hi> confirming Grace to ſome <hi>Angels,</hi> and not to others, to preſerve them <hi>from</hi> Sin,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:35088:6"/>according to the Sovereignty of his Will, without reference to their deſert. This <hi>Grace</hi> God granted to the <hi>elect</hi> Angels; who has one of the <hi>Antients</hi> duly obſerves) were, <hi>Amplius adjuti,</hi> more aſſiſted by the Grace of God than the other that fell: and what <hi>reaſon</hi> can be alledged for this, but merely the abſolute Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reignty, and <hi>free</hi> Pleaſure of God? And here we muſt <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieſce</hi> after all our vain and tedious Diſputes. <hi>Behold, in this thou art not juſt, God is greater than Man, why doſt thou ſtrive a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him; for he giveth not account of any of his matters.</hi> Job 33.12, 13. <hi>Wilt thou condemn him that is moſt juſt? Is it fit to ſay to a King, thou art wicked? How much leſs to him that accepts not the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of Princes, nor regardeth the rich more than the poor?</hi> Job 34.17, 18, 19. Yea, indeed, this great God (who governs all perſons and things) is moſt juſt; his <hi>Will</hi> being the eternal <hi>Rule</hi> of Righteouſneſs. <hi>Juſtice</hi> may be conſidered <hi>two</hi> ways; the one is, when things are carried towards Men, according to their Works. The other is, when a Man doth no other thing than he hath <hi>power</hi> to do; as in executing the power that God hath given him over the <hi>inferior</hi> Creatures. Thus we are juſt, though We kill <hi>Sheep</hi> or Oxen, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> not in reference to any Works of <hi>theirs;</hi> but only in reference to our own <hi>neceſſary</hi> uſe, and that lawful power which God hath given us, to make uſe of theſe Creatures, and to ſerve our own turns of them. And thus, God is not <hi>unjuſt</hi> or unrighteous, but <hi>moſt</hi> righteous and juſt in ſhewing <hi>Mercy</hi> on ſome, and not on others; in giving the Grace of Faith and Repentance to ſome, and not to others, when there is no difference between them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 8.</head>
               <p>It is the great duty and <hi>Concernment</hi> of all thoſe perſons to whom the Goſpel is preached; be they <hi>rich</hi> or poor, noble or ignoble, learned or unlearned, <hi>moral</hi> or prophane, to deny themſelves, and believe on Chriſt for everlaſting Life and Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, without queſtioning the ſecret <hi>Eternal</hi> Decrees and Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes of God concerning them in particular. When Men are in danger of <hi>drowning,</hi> if a <hi>Rope</hi> be caſt out, with a Command that they ſhould lay hold on it for their ſafety, will any of them be
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:35088:6"/>ſo fooliſh as to neglect the means of their ſafety, till the ſecret purpoſe and meaning of him that caſt out the <hi>Rope</hi> be particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly known concerning them? Or if a <hi>rich</hi> Man throw Mony a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the <hi>Poor,</hi> requiring them to accept of it; will any of them refuſe it, till he certainly know the ſecret intent and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of the rich Man concerning him in particular? Although the Goſpel doth not <hi>exprefly</hi> fignifie, that this or that Man ſhall, In the <hi>Event,</hi> actually believe on Chriſt, and be ſaved; yet the <hi>Goſpel</hi> makes known to the Sons of Men, that it is their duty to accept and embrace the Lord Jeſns, as he is freely offered to Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners; and that whoſoever will be juſtified and ſaved, muſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve on him: <hi>He that hath the Son hath life, but he that hath not the Son hath not life: He that believeth on Chriſt ſhall be ſaved, but he that believeth not ſhall be damned.</hi> Faith and Salvation are ſo <hi>indiviſibly</hi> joyned together, that whereſoever the one is, there the other neceſſarily and infallibly followeth. <hi>Conſider,</hi> 1. That where God affords the <hi>means</hi> of Grace, there the outward Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation of the Goſpel is alike to all, both <hi>Elect</hi> and Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate: We <hi>invite,</hi> we wooe, we <hi>intreat</hi> all to come in, and be reconciled to God, not knowing in particular who are elect of <hi>reprobate</hi> in reſpect of the Eternal <hi>Decrees</hi> of God; we offer Chriſt freely to all that will come: <hi>Whoſoever will, let him take the water of life freely,</hi> Rev. 22.17. Chriſt is tendered as an All ſufficient <hi>Saviour</hi> to all that hear the Goſpel, with a Command to believe; and a promiſe that, <hi>Whoſoever</hi> (none excepted) <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth, ſhall be ſaved.</hi> And though none can ſavingly believe without God's <hi>Special</hi> Grace, yet all thoſe that finally reject this Tender of the Goſpel are left without excuſe. 2. As none of us are <hi>expreſly</hi> mentioned by <hi>Name</hi> in the Goſpel, ſo neither are we excluded by Name. There we find, that <hi>Chriſt died for the world, for ſinners, for the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodly, for Enemies.</hi> Rom. 5.6, 8, 10. <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.16, 17.1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.15.1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.2. Which words are <hi>comprehenſive,</hi> and will take in all ſorts of <hi>ſinners</hi> that will <hi>hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily</hi> receive and embrace the Lord Jeſus. <hi>Him that cometh to me</hi> (ſaith our <hi>bleſſed</hi> Saviour) <hi>I will in no wiſe caſt out.</hi> Joh. 6.37. And what though our <hi>ſins</hi> be exceeding great and <hi>hainous,</hi> yet let us remember, that forgiveneſs and <hi>pardon</hi> of all ſins of what <hi>number</hi> or nature foever they be) is freely offered and promiſed
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:35088:7"/>to every one that ſhall <hi>cordially</hi> accept thereof. So that it mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters not ſo much, what our Sins have formerly been, as whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we are <hi>now</hi> heartily willing to cloſe with Jeſus Chriſt, for pardon of, and power againſt Sin. 3. We cannot perform a more <hi>acceptable</hi> Service and Obedience to God, than to believe on Chriſt, and heartily embrace the offer of his Grace (as being poor, loſt, condemned Sinners in our ſelves) <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.29. <hi>With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out this, all other works are but dead works.</hi> Heb. 9.14. Heb. 11.4, 5, 6. <hi>He that believes not, doth what he can to make God a liar.</hi> 1 Joh. 5.10. <hi>And he that believes on the Son of God, ſets to his ſeal, that God is true,</hi> Joh. 3.33.4. Such as have truly <hi>repented</hi> of their Sins, and do caſt and roul themſelves (in the ſenſe of their own unworthineſs) upon the <hi>perfect</hi> Righteouſneſs and Merits of Chriſt (as held forth in the Promiſes of the Goſpel) have the <hi>witneſs</hi> in themſelves of their <hi>Election, Juſtification</hi> and <hi>Adoption,</hi> and are free from the danger of <hi>Reprobation</hi> and final <hi>Obduration;</hi> though at preſent they are ſenſible of, and do groan under much <hi>hardnſs</hi> of heart and corruption. <hi>'Tis God that juſtifies, 'tis Chriſt that died for them: Who therefore ſhall condemn them? who ſhall lay any thing to their charge?</hi> Rom. 8.1, 32.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 9.</head>
               <p>Whereas God is often ſaid in Scripture to <hi>harden</hi> the hearts of Men, <hi>Exod.</hi> 4.21. <hi>Exod.</hi> 9.16. <hi>Deut.</hi> 2.30. <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.18. Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly God doth not <hi>harden</hi> Men's hearts (as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> rightly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves) <hi>Infundendo Malitiam,</hi> but <hi>Non Infundendo Gratiam:</hi> 'Tis not by <hi>infuſing</hi> any <hi>evil</hi> into the heart, but by witholding, and not communicating his <hi>Grace</hi> to it. As the <hi>Water</hi> is congealed and frozen by the abſence of the Sun: how? not by imparting coldneſs, but by not imparting heat and influence. Hardneſs of heart, as it is Sin and Rebellion againſt God, ſo God hath nothing to do with it; but it muſt be put upon the Score of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan,</hi> and the Corruption of Man's Nature. God <hi>hardeneth</hi> not the hearts of his <hi>own</hi> people as he hardeneth the <hi>Reprobates:</hi> for though he <hi>hide</hi> his <hi>face,</hi> and ſuſpend the comfortable <hi>Influences</hi> of his Spirit from them for a <hi>moment,</hi> to try and humble them under the Senſe of their Corruption; yet with everlaſting kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:35088:7"/>he will embrace them; <hi>Iſa.</hi> 54.8. God is ſaid to harden in withdrawing his Grace, and ordering and diſpoſing even Men's evil Actions to that <hi>end</hi> which he hath propounded to himſelf, and in uſing the means which the Corruption and <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignity</hi> of Man's heart and nature perverteth to his own deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. Thus God, in his wiſe Providence, ordereth and over-ruleth the <hi>Action</hi> of Hardning, but Man himſelf is the Cauſe of the <hi>Obliquity</hi> and ſinfulneſs of the Action. In Scripture we find that God <hi>hardeneth,</hi> Satan hardeneth, and <hi>Man</hi> hardeneth his own heart: <hi>Man</hi> as the inſtrument, Satan as the Worker and <hi>Effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient;</hi> God as the <hi>Supreme</hi> Judge, over-ruling every Action, and diſpoſing of it to his own Glory, either in a way of Mercy or <hi>Juſtice.</hi> As in a <hi>Ship,</hi> Man is as the <hi>Mariner</hi> that worketh; <hi>Satan</hi> the evil Spirit, as the Wind and Weather that tempteth and <hi>moveth;</hi> and God as the <hi>Steers-man,</hi> that directeth and govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth all. Like as then the <hi>Sun</hi> hardneth the Clay, and the <hi>Rain</hi> brings forth Weeds, not of it ſelf, but by reaſon of the Nature of the <hi>Soil</hi> which it influenceth: So, by the Providence and <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration</hi> of God, after a moſt ſecret (yet juſt and holy manner) the <hi>hearts</hi> of wicked men come to be hardened more and more; but the only <hi>culpable</hi> Cauſe thereof is in themſelves, and in the Corruption of their Nature, and not in God.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 10.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hardneſs</hi> of heart is either natural and inbred (which we bring with us into the World) or elſe it is <hi>acquired</hi> and voluntary: and this is an extinguiſhing of that common <hi>Light,</hi> and Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and Ingenuity which is in Men; whereby they make their hearts as <hi>hard</hi> as an <hi>Adamant</hi> Stone, and wilfully eſtrange themſelves from God; or elſe it is an Additional Hardneſs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted by the juſt hand of God upon them, as a puniſhment of their <hi>Sin: Thus God hardned the hearts of Pharaoh and others, giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them up to a reprobate ſenſe, and the vile luſts of their own hearts.</hi> Rom. 1.24, 28. <hi>Again,</hi> Hardneſs of heart is either <hi>felt</hi> or not <hi>felt.</hi> The Reprobate (who is given up to hardneſs of heart, and <hi>ſearedneſs</hi> of Conſcience) is not ſenſible of that <hi>dreadful</hi> ſpiritual Judgment which he lies under, nor doth he <hi>bewail</hi> it:
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:35088:8"/>but hardneſs <hi>felt,</hi> when a Man ſees and feels, with grief and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, the deadneſs, and hardneſs, and <hi>benummedneſs</hi> of his own <hi>heart,</hi> which doth not <hi>relent</hi> (as it ſhould do) at the threatnings and <hi>promiſes</hi> of God; nor is it <hi>thawed</hi> and melted with the <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies</hi> and Loving kindneſſes of God: ſuch a <hi>ſenſible</hi> hardneſs is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident to God's own Children; who often complain of it, and groan under it, as a great and heavy <hi>burthen. O Lord</hi> (ſay they) <hi>why haſt thou made us to err from thy ways, and hardned our hearts from thy fear.</hi> Iſa. 63.17.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 11.</head>
               <p>Are we <hi>ſenſible</hi> of the hardneſs and <hi>ſtonyneſs</hi> of our hearts? and would we be cured of this great Evil? Then 1. Let us dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently ſearch and examine whether we do not <hi>indulge</hi> our ſelves in ſome ſecret Sin or other; which being unrepented of, will <hi>harden</hi> the heart. 2. Let us <hi>conſider</hi> the greatneſs and <hi>goodneſs</hi> of that Divine Majeſty, againſt whom our hearts are <hi>hardned:</hi> this will be a <hi>means</hi> to ſoften them. <hi>Deut.</hi> 10.16, 17, 18. <hi>Job</hi> 23.15, 16. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 95.3, 8, 9.2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 30.8, 9.3. Above all other things, let us <hi>meditate</hi> on Chriſt <hi>crucified,</hi> and lay our hard and <hi>frozen</hi> hearts before the <hi>hot</hi> Beams of the <hi>Sun</hi> of Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. <hi>Mal.</hi> 4.2. that they may ſenſibly feel the <hi>force</hi> of his gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious influence; and ſo, looking up to him by Faith (whom we have pierced with our Sins,) we may thereupon <hi>melt</hi> and <hi>mourn for our ſins, as one that mourns for his only child.</hi> Zach. 12.10. 'Tis obſerved of the <hi>Diamond</hi> (whoſe extreme <hi>hardneſs</hi> cannot be mol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified, either by the force of Iron, or the violence of the Fire) that if it be ſteeped in the <hi>hot</hi> blood of a <hi>Goat,</hi> it preſently diſſolves. The Iron Hammer of the <hi>Law</hi> will not <hi>melt</hi> and <hi>ſoften</hi> our hard and ſtubborn hearts; but if, by true Faith and Meditation, we <hi>bath</hi> and plunge then in the pretious Blood of the true <hi>Scape<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goat,</hi> the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, this will break and <hi>melt</hi> the heart (though it be as hard as an <hi>Adamant.</hi>) The ſacred <hi>Blood</hi> of the Phyſician <hi>cureſ</hi> the Diſeaſe of the Patient.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>O rare</hi> Phyſician; <hi>thou that ſhedſt thy</hi> Blood,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And gav'ſt thy</hi> Life <hi>to do poor Sinners</hi> Good.</l>
               </q>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
